Guide to the Coburn Britton Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Coburn Britton papers
1919-1997
YCAL MSS 650
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.91
(6 boxes)
The collection contains correspondence, writings, and personal papers documenting the life and literary activities of American poet and publisher Coburn Britton. The correspondence features a nearly three-decade long exchange between Britton and Jack Sullivan, some of which was compiled and published as Letters from Jack: Sex & Hell in Manhattan and Backwoods Maine (2002). In addition, there are small groups of correspondence with others, including Glenway Wescott, Edward Dahlberg, and Lincoln Kirstein, dating chiefly from the 1970s, as well as approximately 150 postcards from graphic artist Willyum Rowe, with whom Britton collaborated on An ABeCedarium for Poets and Readers (1989). Many if not most of the postcards from Rowe are decorated, for example, with cutouts and stamps, providing a large group of postcard or mail art from the period. Writings include printed versions of Britton's Second Seasons (1982), Lesser Goods and Other Poems (1987), and An ABeCedarium for Poets and Readers (1989), and drafts of the later Adrian Sonnets (1995) and shorter works. Others materials include photographs of family and friends, printed materials, and documents.
Britton, Coburn
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Elizabeth Harries, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Coburn Haskell Britton (1935-1997)
Coburn Britton was born in Cleveland, Ohio to Mr. and Mrs. Brigham Britton of Bratenahl, Ohio. He attended University School, Deerfield Academy in Massachusetts, Yale University, and Trinity College, Dublin, as a Fulbright scholar, before settling in New York City. Britton was an editor at Doubleday and Company and co-publisher of Horizon Press in the 1960s and then founder of the magazine Prose in 1970. After closing the magazine in 1974 he divided his time between writing poetry and tending to his farm in Hunterdon County, New Jersey. Britton's works include Second Seasons (1982), Lesser Goods and Other Poems (1987), An ABeCedarium for Poets and Readers (1989), and Adrian Sonnets (1995). He died 26 November 1997 in Lebanon, New Jersey.
Biographical information taken from "Paid Notice: Deaths BRITTON, COBURN." New York Times 29 Nov. 1997. Gale Biography In Context. Web. 10 Oct. 2012.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, writings, and personal papers documenting the life and literary activities of American poet and publisher Coburn Britton. The correspondence features a nearly three-decade long exchange between Britton and Jack Sullivan, some of which was compiled and published as Letters from Jack: Sex & Hell in Backwoods Maine (1997). In addition, there are small groups of correspondence with others, including Glenway Wescott, Edward Dahlberg, and Lincoln Kirstein, dating chiefly from the 1970s, as well as approximately 150 postcards from graphic artist Willyum Rowe, with whom Britton collaborated on An ABeCedarium for Poets and Readers (1989). Many if not most of the postcards from Rowe are decorated, for example, with cutouts and stamps, providing a large group of postcard mail art from the period. Writings include printed versions of Britton's Second Seasons (1982), Lesser Goods and Other Poems (1987), and An ABeCedarium for Poets and Readers (1989), and drafts of the later Adrian Sonnets (1995) and shorter works. Others materials include photographs of family and friends, printed materials, and documents.
Arrangement
Organized into one grouping by date of acquisition: June 2002 Acqusition.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors and publishers -- United States; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Publishers and publishing -- United States; Mail art -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographic prints; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Britton, Coburn; Dahlberg, Edward, 1900-1977; Kirstein, Lincoln, 1907-1996; Rowe, William, 1946-; Sullivan, Jack, 1936-; Wescott, Glenway, 1901-1987
- June 2002 Acquisition, 1919-1997; 3.83; (5 boxes)
  - Correspondence with Jack Sullivan, [circa 1971-1997]; 32 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Jack: Sex & Hell in Backwoods Maine, draft, computer printout, [circa 1997]; 5 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Jack Sullivan, 1971-1978; 17 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Jack Sullivan, 1989-1979; 4 (Box 2)
  - Letter from unidentified correspondent, 1994 June 9 (Box 2)
  - "Letters to Betsey Harries + Jennifer Whiting...", 1990-1995, undated (Box 2)
  - Printed material, undated (Box 2)
  - Material relating to Margaret Anderson, 1973, undated; 2 (Box 2)
  - Unidentified manuscript, 1954, undated (Box 2)
  - Certificate of Occupancy form, completed (copy), 1968 (Box 2)
  - Material relating to Deerfield, 1952-1954, undated (Box 2)
  - "Letters from the 1950s..." (Box 2)
  - Geneaological and other material, 1977, undated (Box 2)
  - Photograph album and other material, 1964-1975, undated (Box 2)
  - Printed and other material, 1970s (Box 2)
  - Photographs, undated; 2 (Box 2)
  - Letter from [Hussey?], 1973 October 4 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous material, 1942-1962, undated; 3 (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 1919-[195?], undated; 4 (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 1964-1995, undated; 6 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence with Jack Sullivan, 1980-1991; 37 (Box 3)
  - "Adrian letters + poems", undated (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and other material, 1928-1978; 3 (Box 4)
  - "John Pope-Hennessy", 1970-1972 (Box 4)
  - "Robin Magowan", 1972, undated (Box 4)
  - "Paul Metcalf", 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Glenway Wescott, 1972 (Box 4)
  - "Patrick White", 1970 (Box 4)
  - Clippings and other material, 1970-1985, undated (Box 4)
  - "Edward Dahlberg", 1976-1977, undated (Box 4)
  - Lincoln Kirstein, 1970-1973 (Box 4)
  - "Jonathan Williams", 1970-1973 (Box 4)
  - Alex Gildzen, 1970 November 16 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous material, 1945-1995, undated (Box 4)
  - Unidentified poem, undated (Box 4)
  - Stories by Britton, undated (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1978, 1996; 2 (Box 4)
  - "Letters about Adrian Sonnets", 1996, undated (Box 4)
  - "Willyum Rowe", 1972-1981, undated; 9 (Box 4)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes photographs
  - "Sonetto XXV," drafts, 1997, undated (Box 4)
  - "Tovarish Archimedes and Co.," draft by Howard [Hassey?], undated
  - Pastel by [Lunda?] Britton, 1983 November
  - Printed materials, 1982-1989; 2 (Box 4)
  - "Colby's Own Stuff", 1965-1995, undated; 3 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence and other material, 1954-1996, undated; 4 (Box 5)
- Oversize, 0.08; (1 box)
  - Photographs, 1919, [195?] (Box 6)
  - Clipping, 1985 December 8 (Box 6)
  - "Tovarish Archimedes and Co.," draft by Howard [Hassey?], undated (Box 6)
  - Pastel by [Lunda?] Britton, 1983 November (Box 6)